Finding Aid for the Nashville as Historical Laboratory Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Nashville as Historical Laboratory Collection
1977-1978
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0311
.42 linear_feet
Biography/History
The research and subsequent manuscripts in this collection were completed by students enrolled in Vanderbilt University, History 295 (Nashville and the Urban South), in Spring Semester 1977 and Fall Semester 1978. The summary of the course and discussion of the papers, in the context of Nashville history, was written by Professor Don Harrison Doyle. The 26 student papers cover the time period of 1870-1940.
Scope and Contents
This .42 linear feet collection contains 26 file folders arranged in alphabetical order.
- Course Summary
  - Doyle, Don Harrison
    - Nashville as Historical Laboratory for Teaching Undergraduates
- Manuscripts - Student
  - Banker, David
    - Black Ideology in Nashville, 1907-1913
  - Beach, Julia
    - Belle Meade Country Club and Urbanization, c., 1900-1920
  - Bennett, Andy D.
    - Rural Migration from Dickson County to Nashville, 1920-1940
  - Bryan, Eleanor W.
    - The Negro in Nashville from, 1900-1920
  - Camacho, Lisa
    - Three Case Studies of Nashville Families in Business
  - Christian, Jeanne A
    - Suburbanizing Nashville, 1880-1920: Familial Differentiation Within Economic Development
  - Cox, Susan E.
    - The Nashville Elite:, 1896-1907
  - Cramer, Cynthia
    - Boosterism in Nashville, 1880-1910
  - Dozier, Steve R.
    - Prohibition and the Enforcement of the Nashville Police Department, (1905-1933)
  - Everton, Glenn
    - The Black Business Community of Nashville
  - Fisher, Earl
    - Nashville Civic Elites, 1870-1895
  - Griffin, Neill
    - The Jim Crow Streetcar Boycott in Nashville
  - Hoover, Hilary
    - The Tennessee Centennial Exposition, Nashville, Tennessee, 1897
  - Israel, R.D.
    - Donald Davidson and the Development of Agrarianism in the 1920’s
  - Kelly, Paul K.
    - The Nashville Elite, 1910-1925
  - London, Kathy L.
    - The Belmont Neighborhood 1900-1920: Prevailing Southernism
  - Morgan, Ann Ward
    - The Black Man’s Compromise Between Booker T. Washington and W. E. B. duBois in Nashville – 1905
  - Neyland, Thomas
    - The Development of Nashville’s Park System, 1901-1935
  - Powell, James
    - Politicians and Public Policy in Nashville in the 1870’s and the 1920’s
  - Price, Amy
    - Urbanization of Nashville from 1908-1917: The Role of Commercial And Civic Clubs
  - Ramirez, Mike
    - The Lost Cause in a New South City: Nashville, 1890-1910
  - Riley, Mark B.
    - Edgefield: A Study of Nashville’s First Suburb*
  - Steckler, David
    - The Death of the Brothel
  - Swann, Susan E.
    - The Twilight of a Walking City: The Nashville Waterfront, 1880 and After
  - Young, Cindy
    - The Growth and Development of the Richland-West End Neighborhood
  - *Revised version in Tennessee Historical Quarterly 37(1978): 133-54.